Register of the Russkoe istoricheskoe obshchestvo v Amerikie Records
Hoover Institution Archives
Russkoe istoricheskoe obshchestvo v Amerikie records,
1876-1956
2000C41
Russkoe istoricheskoe obshchestvo v Amerikie
5 microfilm reels (0.75 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, reports, financial records, writings, membership lists, printed matter, and photographs, relating to the study of Russian contributions to American history.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2000.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Location of Originals
Originals in: Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco.
Administrative History
Russian-American historical association.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains the records of the Russkoe istoricheskoe obshchestvo v Amerikie (Russian Historical Society in America). Its founder and first president was A. P. Farafontov (1937-1940). The second president of the Society was an engineer, Mikhail Dem'ianovich Sedykh (1940-1948). The records consist their correspondence, writings and other materials collected by them in the course of the organization's activities, which included aid in the restoration of Fort Ross, California, celebrations honoring the 200th anniversary of the European discovery of Alaska (1941), and other cultural events. Also present are writings and correspondence by prominent émigrés, such as A. A. Kersnovskii, P. V. Shkurkin, S. G. Svatikov, and others. Almost all the records of the collection date from 1933 to 1948, but the scrapbook on M. D. Sedykh (Office File/Members' papers/Sedykh) expands the temporal bounds to those shown in the series description.
Detailed processing and preservation microfilming for these materials were made possible by a generous grant from the National Endowment for the Humanities and by matching funds from the Hoover Institution and the Museum of Russian Culture. The grant also provides depositing a microfilm copy in the Hoover Institution Archives. The original materials remain in the Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco, as its property. A transfer table indicating corresponding box and reel numbers is available at the Hoover Institution Archives.
The Hoover Institution assumes all responsibility for notifying users that they must comply with the copyright law of the United States (Title 17 United States Code) and Hoover Rules for the Use and Reproduction of Archival Materials.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Russians--United States--Study and teaching.; Russia; United States.
Series Description
- Office File, 1907-1956. (Box 1-5)
  Activity reports, charter, clippings, correspondence, financial records, membership lists, members' papers, and other materials arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Subject File, 1876-1948. (Box 5)
  Brochures, bulletins, clippings, correspondence, leaflets, writings and other printed matter, arranged alphabetically by heading
- Photographs, n.d. (Box 5)
  Three photographs, one possibly depicting M. D. Sedykh, and two photographs of flags created by L. Ia. Bukharin
Container List
- OFFICE FILE, 1907-1956 (Box 1)
  - Activity reports, 1938-1940 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Address lists. (Folder 1: 2)
    Includes appended correspondence concerning membership dues, 1937
  - Applications for membership (Folder 1: 3)
  - Charter, 1937 (Folder 1: 4)
  - Clippings about or mentioning the RIO (Folder 1: 5)
  - Correspondence issuing from and addressed to A. P. Farafontov and M. D. Sedykh as representatives of the Society., For correspondence between them see below, General/Internal correspondence
    - General
      - General, 1937-1945 and undated (Folder 1: 6)
      - Correspondence with U.S. cities bearing Russian place names, 1939 (Folder 1: 7)
      - Correspondence with various individuals and organizations relating to celebrations of the 200th anniversary of the discovery of Alaska, 1941 (Folder 1: 8)
      - Internal correspondence, 1937-1948 (Folder 1: 9)
    - Unidentified, 1938-1939 (Folder 1: 10)
    - Abrosimova, A. T., 1938-1945 and undated (Folder 1: 11)
    - Aleksei, Bishop of Alaska, 1940 (Folder 1: 12)
    - Al'tman, A., 1940-1941 (Folder 1: 13)
    - Andrews, Clarence L., 1937-1942 (Folder 1: 14)
    - Aref'ev, Vasilii Nikolaevich, 1937-1939 (Folder 1: 15)
    - Association of Former Russian Naval Officers in America, Inc., 1938-1948. (Folder 1: 16)
      Includes some issues of the association's bulletins
    - Baranov, Makarii, Rev., 1940-1943 (Folder 1: 17)
    - Baryborova, Sofiia Nikolaevna, n.d. (Folder 1: 18)
    - Benzeman, Khristofor Martynovich, 1940-1944 (Folder 1: 19)
    - Borzov, Nikolai Viktorovich, 1940-1944 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Bunin, Ivan Mikhailovich, 1937-1942 (Folder 2: 2)
    - Chernavin, Ioann, Rev., 1938 (Folder 2: 3)
    - Dobrovidov, Vladimir Nikolaevich, 1941-1942 (Folder 2: 4)
    - Dudorov, Boris Petrovich, 1938 (Folder 2: 5)
    - Falenberg, Nikolai Fedorovich, 1943-1944 (Folder 2: 6)
    - Feofil (Theophilus), Metropolitan of North America, 1938-1944 (Folder 2: 7)
    - Gordenev, Milii Iul'evich, 1938-1942 (Folder 2: 8)
    - Grebenshchikov, Georgii Dmitrievich, 1938 (Folder 2: 9)
    - Karinskii, Nikolai Sergeevich, 1944-1945 (Folder 2: 10)
    - Kokhanik, Petr, Rev., 1938 (Folder 2: 11)
    - Kropotkin, Aleksei Alekseevich, Prince, 1938 (Folder 2: 12)
    - Kuchinskaia, Elena Petrovna, 1943 (Folder 2: 13)
    - Kurganskii, V., 1948 (Folder 2: 14)
    - Lantzeff, George V., 1940-1941 (Folder 2: 15)
    - Lanz, Henry, 1941 (Folder 2: 16)
    - Laub, Anna, 1943 (Folder 2: 17)
    - Lebedev, Boris Pavlovich, 1938-1940 (Folder 2: 18)
    - Lebedev, Vladimir Pavlovich, 1938-1940 (Folder 2: 19)
    - Leontii, Bishop of Chicago, 1940-1945 (Folder 2: 20)
    - Maksutov, Dimitrii D., n.d. (Folder 2: 21)
    - Malozemova, Elizaveta Andreevna, 1940 and undated (Folder 2: 22)
    - Mikhailov, Konstantin Potapovich., See Members' papers/Farafontov, Aleksandr Pavlovich
    - Mladorosskaia partiia, 1937-1939 (Folder 2: 23)
    - Moskov, Evgenii Aleksandrovich, 1937-1939 (Folder 2: 24)
    - Navrotskii, Iurii Aleksandrovich, 1938-1943 (Folder 2: 25)
    - Nikitin, Dmitrii Vladimirovich, 1937-1941 (Folder 2: 26)
    - Novaia zaria, 1937-1938 (Folder 2: 27)
    - Obshchestvo russkikh veteranov velikoi voiny, 1937-1945 (Folder 2: 28)
    - Orlov, Ivan Petrovich, 1940-1942 (Folder 2: 29)
    - Ponomarev, Fedor Petrovich, 1937 (Folder 2: 30)
    - Porokhovshchikov, Petr Sergeevich, 1944 (Folder 2: 31)
    - Prisadskii, Aleksandr, Rev., 1940-1942 (Folder 2: 32)
    - Prishchepenko, Nikolai Iosifovich, 1941-1944 (Folder 2: 33)
    - Rklitskaia, Liudmila (Rklitsky, Ludmila), 1940-1943. (Folder 2: 34)
      Includes lecture programs
    - Rossiia, 1938-1943 (Folder 2: 35)
    - Russian Center, San Francisco, 1940-1941 (Folder 2: 36)
    - Russkoe pravoslavnoe kafolicheskoe obshchestvo vzaimopomoshchi (Russian Orthodox Catholic Mutual Aid Society), 1937-1938 (Folder 2: 37)
    - St. Vladimir's Russian Orthodox Catholic Society of America, 1943-1946 (Folder 2: 38)
    - Schmidt, Adolph E., 1937-1938 (Folder 2: 39)
    - Shapiro, Nadezhda Lazarevna, 1937 (Folder 2: 40)
    - Sharaev, Lev Antonovich, 1940-1941. (Folder 2: 41)
      Includes clipping of Shumanskii's article, "Istoriia knigopechataniia v Rossii," Rossiia, 1938 May 22
    - Shkurkin, Pavel Vasil'evich., See Members' papers/Shkurkin, Pavel Vasil'evich/ Correspondence
    - Shumanskii, Klementii Vasil'evich, 1938-1939 (Folder 2: 42)
    - Svatikov, Sergei Grigor'evich., See Members' papers/Svatikov, Sergei Grigor'evich/ Correspondence
    - Sviet, 1937-1943 (Folder 2: 43)
    - Tel'berg, Georgii Gustavovich, 1944 (Folder 2: 44)
    - Tiurleminskii, Aleksei Ivanovich, 1938-1940 (Folder 2: 45)
    - Tokarev, T. F., 1937-1938 and undated (Folder 2: 46)
    - Tulintsev, Iurii Nikolaevich, 1941 (Folder 2: 47)
    - Vakar, Nikolai Platonovich, 1943-1944 (Folder 2: 48)
    - Vasilii, Grand Duke, 1943-1944., Consists mainly of correspondence with Western Union Telegraph Company regarding refund of payment for undelivered telegram to Grand Duke Vasilii (Folder 2: 49)
    - Vinokurov (Vinokooroff), M. Z., 1937 (Folder 2: 50)
    - Vitalii, Archbishop, 1938 (Folder 2: 51)
  - Financial records, 1937-1946 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - Instructions for affiliates (Folder 3: 2)
  - Library of the Russkoe istoricheskoe obshchestvo v Amerikie. (Folder 3: 3)
    Includes clippings, notes, lists of publications received
  - Membership lists. (Folder 3: 4)
    May also include names of prospective members
  - Members' papers
    - Farafontov, Aleksandr Pavlovich
      - Letter of recommendation for, 1944 (Folder 3: 5)
      - Writings, 1938-[1940] and undated
        - "Chashka chaia Russkago Istoricheskago obshchestva v Amerikie," n.d. (Folder 3: 6)
          Typescript
        - "K konchinie ottsa Aleksandra Viacheslavova," n.d. (Folder 3: 7)
        - "K predstoiashchemu semidesiatilietiiu P. V. Shkurkina," n.d. (Folder 3: 8)
        - "K 126-ti-lietnei godovshchinie Forta Ross," n.d. (Folder 3: 9)
        - "Ostatki russkoi stariny," n.d. (Folder 3: 10)
        - Untitled, n.d. (Folder 3: 11)
          Newspaper clipping
        - "V Russkom istoricheskom obshchestvie," n.d. (Folder 3: 12)
          Holograph. Includes undated letter to P. P. Balakshin
        - Malen'kii rabotnik, 1913-1915. (Folder 3: 13)
          Four issues of a mimeographed holograph and typed periodical for schoolchildren edited by A. P. Farafontov
        - Bazarnaia vydumka, 1915 summer. (Folder 3: 14)
          One issue of a mimeographed holograph children's journal, probably edited by A. P. Farafontov
        - "Znaete-li vy," 1937-1938. (Folder 3: 15)
          Holograph and typescript. Series of newspaper columns
        - "Zhizn' za Khrista," 1938 August 21. (Folder 3: 16)
        - "Konstantin Potapovivh Mikhailov," [1939 January 2]. (Folder 3: 17)
          Typescript. Includes background materials such as correspondence with Mikhailov, 1938-1939, photographs of him and Mikhailov's newspaper articles and letters to the editor, 1933-1938
        - Letter to the editor, Novaia Zaria, 1939 January 6. (Folder 3: 18)
          Holograph
        - "O diadie Vlasie," [1940]. (Folder 3: 19)
    - Kiiashchenko, Georgii Titovich. (Folder 3: 20)
      Includes condolences on his death, the charter of a society to honor the memory of Nicholas II, with attached correspondence, 1938, and #14 (1931) of Vera i pravda
    - Mogil'nikov, Georgii Semenovich. (Folder 3: 21)
      Includes issue of Budni (San Francisco, #6, 1938 Dec. 2) and Russkii listok (Seattle, #47, 1938 Sept. 21), as well as typescript entitled "Za kogo golosovat'," [1936]
    - Sedykh (Sedich), Mikhail Dem'ianovich
      - General. (Folder 3: 22)
        Materials relating to his career as an engineer
      - Scrapbook. (Box-folder 4: 1)
        Includes correspondence, photographs, writings, and printed matter relating to the life and career of M. D. Sedykh
    - Shkurkin, Pavel Vasil'evich
      - Correspondence with A. P. Farafontov, 1935-1943 and undated (Folder 4: 2)
      - Writings
        - "Khranilishcha kul'tury," n.d. (Folder 4: 3)
        - "Vremia Vladimira Sviatogo i ego rol' v istorii," Novaia zaria, 1938 August 4. (Folder 4: 4)
          Printed copy
      - Miscellany. (Folder 4: 5)
        Clipping about Shkurkin and notes by Farafontov regarding his visit to San Francisco in April 1939
    - Svatikov, Sergei Grigor'evich
      - Correspondence with A. P. Farafontov, 1937-1939 (Folder 4: 6)
      - Writing, "Amerika i russkie poety XVIII-go vieka," [1938]. (Folder 4: 7)
      - Miscellany (Folder 4: 8)
  - Memoranda (Folder 4: 9)
  - Minutes of meetings, 1937-1941. (Folder 4: 10)
    Includes notices of meetings and related material
  - Publications
    - Iubileinyi sbornik, 1741-1941, [1942]
      - General (Folder 4: 11)
      - Printed copy (Folder 4: 12)
      - Correspondence, 1941-1946 (Box-folder 5: 1)
    - Zapiski Russkago Istoricheskago Obshchestva v Amerikie
      - General. (Folder 5: 2)
        Editorial notes and drafts, including proposed tables of contents, reviews, and typed draft of article by A. Kersnovskii, entitled "Iz proshlago Rossii," n.d. Typescript
      - Printed copies (issues dated 1938 October and 1939 March) (Folder 5: 3)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1876-1948.
  Clippings, correspondence and printed matter
  - Bazhenov, Anatolii Dmitrievich (Folder 5: 4)
  - Den' russkogo rebenka (Folder 5: 5)
  - Fire departments--California--San Francisco. (Folder 5: 6)
    Includes information on the Veteran Firemen's Association of San Francisco
  - Fort Ross, California. (Folder 5: 7)
    Includes clippings, correspondence (mainly with officials of the California State Division of Beaches and Parks, as well as with Metropolitan Feofil and others) relating to restoration activities, 1939-1947
  - General Platoff's Don Cossack Choir (Folder 5: 8)
  - Greek, Russian, Slavonian Orthodox Eastern Church and Benevolent Society (Folder 5: 9)
  - Holy Trinity Russian Eastern Orthodox Cathedral, San Francisco (Folder 5: 10)
  - Museum of Russian Culture, San Francisco (Folder 5: 11)
  - Russkii kul'turno-istoricheskii muzei, Prague, Czechoslovakia (Folder 5: 12)
  - Russkoe sel'sko-khoziaistvennoe obshchestvo (Folder 5: 13)
  - Tomaroff, Aron (Folder 5: 14)
  - Miscellany. (Folder 5: 15)
    Brochures, clippings, and leaflets
- PHOTOGRAPHS, n.d. (Folder 5: 16)
  One photograph of an unidentified individual, possibly M. D. Sedykh, and two photographs of flags created by L. Ia. Bukharin